<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: apple | xixitalk's snippet]]></title>
  <link href="http://xixitalk.github.io/blog/categories/apple/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://xixitalk.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-02T22:28:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://xixitalk.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[xixitalk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[苹果应用商店启用https，中国要对应用进行审查]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.io/blog/2012/12/20/apple-adopted-https-in-app-store-china-threatens-to-censor-apps/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T15:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.io/blog/2012/12/20/apple-adopted-https-in-app-store-china-threatens-to-censor-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>来源:<a href="https://en.greatfire.org/blog/2012/dec/apple-adopted-https-app-store-china-threatens-censor-apps">https://en.greatfire.org/blog/2012/dec/apple-adopted-https-app-store-china-threatens-censor-apps</a></p>

<h2 id="apple-adopted-https-in-app-store-china-threatens-to-censor-apps">Apple adopted https in App Store. China threatens to censor apps.</h2>
<p>##苹果应用商店启用https，中国要对应用进行审查
Submitted by percy on Thu, Dec 20, 2012
由percy于2012.12.20 星期四提交</p>

<p>Recently, China threatens to require every app to have a license in order to go on sale, as reported by <a href="http://cn.nytimes.com/article/business/2012/12/19/cc19weiwuhui/">New York times</a>. The time is too coincidental as Apple adopted https on iTunes for searching and downloading Apps.<br />
最近，<a href="http://cn.nytimes.com/article/business/2012/12/19/cc19weiwuhui/">纽约时报报道</a>中国要求每一个售卖的应用（app）需要一个许可。与此同时，苹果的iTunes搜索和下载应用都启用https链接。</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Before this adoption, searching for certain keywords such as “vpn” would lead to a connection reset on iTunes and visiting the page for certain Apps, such as VPN Express would also <a href="https://en.greatfire.org/itunes.apple.com/app/vpn-express-best-mobile-vpn/id375584677%3Fmt%3D8">cause a reset</a>, which means there is no way for users in China to search for or download certain Apps even if they are available in China App Store.<br />
在启用https之前，在iTunes搜索某些特定的关键词，如“VPN”会导致<a href="https://en.greatfire.org/itunes.apple.com/app/vpn-express-best-mobile-vpn/id375584677%3Fmt%3D8">连接重置</a>，访问某些特定的应用，如VPN express也会导致连接重置，这以为着即使在中国区的苹果应用商店的某些应用，位于中国的用户也无法搜索和下载。</p>

<p>But because now https is implemented by Apple on almost all connection to iTunes server, Great Firewall of China has no way to selectively block connection to certain contents. <a href="https://en.greatfire.org/https/itunes.apple.com/app/vpn-express-best-mobile-vpn/id375584677%3Fmt%3D8">A test to the same link</a> mentioned above with https  protocol yields no censorship.<br />
现在因为苹果iTunes服务器的连接几乎全部切换到https，中国防火墙没有办法对某些内容选择进行连接阻止。<a href="https://en.greatfire.org/https/itunes.apple.com/app/vpn-express-best-mobile-vpn/id375584677%3Fmt%3D8">一个测试连接</a>表明通过https协议审查失效了。</p>

<p>This change provides a commercial platform in China(China App Store uses CNY for payment) not subject to the arbitrary censorship of the government. For example, opendoor an app dedicated to circumventing the Internet is on sale on China App Store and users are willing to pay to remove ads in the app. Any other trading platform, such as Taobao(Chinese version of ebay) is actively censoring Internet Circumvention tools and selling anti-censorship tools there is not possible.<br />
这个变化发生一个商业平台上（中国苹果商店使用人民币支付），它不受专制的审查系统管制。例如，一个在中国区苹果应用售卖的opendoor应用，它可以提供网络代理功能，用户愿意为去掉广告而付钱。其他交易平台，例如淘宝（中国版的ebay）正在积极的审查网络代理工具，在那里售卖反审查工具几乎不可能了。</p>

<p>Therefore, it is highly likely that the government have noticed this loophole in its censorship net, and is now trying to close it.<br />
综上所述，很大的可能显示政府已经注意到审查系统的这个漏洞，现在正在尝试尽力堵上这个漏洞。</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
