<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | xixitalk's snippet]]></title>
  <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-03T19:15:12+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[xixitalk]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[达尔文奖]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/27/death-for-sesame/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T18:59:21+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/27/death-for-sesame</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>新闻来源<a href="http://news.xinhuanet.com/legal/2013-06/27/c_124918715.htm">http://news.xinhuanet.com/legal/2013-06/27/c_124918715.htm</a></p>

<p>女儿手机掉粪坑，下粪坑捞手机被毒倒，父母赶到也被毒倒。</p>

<!--more-->

<p>无独有偶，<a href="http://csxb.bandao.cn/data/20120917/html/32/content_6.html">北爱尔兰也发生过一条宠物狗掉粪坑，一家四口为救它死了仨</a>，幸存那个人也因吸入大量的粪便和沼气，肺部、食管、呼吸道等器官受损严重。</p>

<p><a href="http://www.darwinawards.com/">达尔文奖</a>奖给那些“让自己愚蠢的基因不再自由地传播出去”，对人类的进化做出了贡献了的人们。维基百科：<a href="https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E8%BE%BE%E5%B0%94%E6%96%87%E5%A5%96">达尔文奖</a>。</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[穆斯林禁食猪肉常见问答]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/23/PORK-FORBIDDEN/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-23T15:42:11+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/23/PORK-FORBIDDEN</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>第一个信息来源 <a href="http://www.irf.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=394%3Apork-forbidden&amp;catid=71%3Amost-common-questions-asked-by-non-muslim&amp;Itemid=199">FAQs Most Common Questions asked by Non Muslims：PORK FORBIDDEN</a></p>

<p>第二个信息来源 <a href="http://www.islamicvoice.com/february.99/zakir.htm">Questions Commonly Asked by Non-Muslims - VI : Why is Pork Forbidden?</a>,和第一个信息地址的内容大部分相同，比第一个信息更正式一些。</p>

<p>说明：下面是穆斯林向非穆斯林说明他们不吃猪肉的几点原因。这里尊重宗教信仰自由，转载此处并无冒犯之意，原因说明本意以英文为准，翻译不准确的地方请留言。作者是<a href="http://www.irf.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=22&amp;Itemid=54">Dr. Zakir Naik</a>，他是<a href="http://www.irf.net/">Islamic Research Foundation</a>的President。</p>

<p>PORK FORBIDDEN<br />
禁食猪肉</p>

<p>Question:
Why is the eating of pork forbidden in Islam?<br />
问：为什么穆斯林禁止食用猪肉？</p>

<p>Answer:
The fact that consumption of pork is prohibited in Islam is well-known. The following points explain various aspects of this prohibition:<br />
答：大家都知道穆斯林禁食猪肉，下面将阐述这个习惯的几点原因。</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="pork-prohibited-in-the-quran">1. Pork prohibited in the Qur’an</h3>

<h3 id="section">1. 《古兰经》里禁食猪肉</h3>
<p>The Qur’an prohibits the consumption of pork in no less than four different places. It is prohibited in 2:173, 5:3, 6:145 and 16:115.</p>

<p>“Forbidden to you (for food) are: dead meat, blood, the flesh of swine, and that on which hath been invoked the name of other than Allah.”</p>

<p>[Al Qur’an 5:3]</p>

<p>The above verses of the Glorious Qur’an are sufficient to satisfy a Muslim as to why pork is forbidden.</p>

<h3 id="pork-prohibited-in-the-bible">2. Pork prohibited in the Bible</h3>

<h3 id="section-1">2. 《圣经》里禁食猪肉</h3>
<p>The Christian is likely to be convinced by his religious scriptures. The Bible prohibits the consumption of pork, in the Book of Leviticus:</p>

<p>“And the swine, though he divide the hoof, and be cloven footed, yet he cheweth not the cud; he is unclean to you.”</p>

<p>“Of their flesh shall ye not eat, and their carcase shall ye not touch, they are unclean to you.”</p>

<p>[Book of Leviticus 11:7-8]</p>

<p>Pork is also prohibited in the Bible in the Book of Deuteronomy:</p>

<p>“And the swine, because it divideth the hoof, yet cheweth not the cud, it is unclean unto you. Ye shall not eat of their flesh, nor touch their dead carcase.”</p>

<p>[Book of Deuteronomy 14:8]</p>

<p>A similar prohibition is repeated in the Bible in the Book of Isaiah Chapter 65 Verses 2-5.</p>

<h3 id="consumption-of-pork-causes-several-diseases">3. Consumption of pork causes several diseases</h3>

<h3 id="section-2">3. 食用猪肉会造成几种疾病</h3>
<p>The other non-Muslims and atheists will agree only if convinced through reason, logic and science. Eating of pork can cause no less than seventy different types of diseases. A person can have various helminths like roundworm, pinworm, hookworm, etc. One of the most dangerous is Taenia Solium, which is in lay man’s terminology called tapeworm. It harbours in the intestine and is very long. Its ova i.e. eggs, enter the blood stream and can reach almost all the organs of the body. If it enters the brain it can cause memory loss. If it enters the heart it can cause heart attack, if it enters the eye it can cause blindness, if it enters the liver it can cause liver damage. It can damage almost all the organs of the body.</p>

<p>Another dangerous helminthes is Trichuris trichiura. A common misconception about pork is that if it is cooked well, these ova die. In a research project undertaken in America, it was found that out of twenty-four people suffering from Trichuris trichiura, twenty-two had cooked the pork very well. This indicates that the ova present in the pork do not die under normal cooking temperature.</p>

<h3 id="pork-has-fat-building-material">4. Pork has fat building material</h3>

<h3 id="section-3">4. 猪肉富含脂肪</h3>
<p>Pork has very little muscle building material and contains excess of fat. This fat gets deposited in the vessels and can cause hypertension and heart attack. It is not surprising that over 50 million Americans suffer from hypertension.</p>

<h3 id="pig-is-one-of-the-filthiest-animals-on-earth">5. Pig is one of the filthiest animals on earth</h3>

<h3 id="section-4">5. 猪是地球上最污秽的动物之一</h3>
<p>The pig is one of the filthiest animals on earth. It lives and thrives on muck, faeces and dirt. It is the best scavenger that I know that God has produced. In the villages they don’t have modern toilets and the villagers excrete in the open air. Very often excreta is cleared by pigs.</p>

<p>Some may argue that in advanced countries like Australia, pigs are bred in very clean and hygienic conditions. Even in these hygienic conditions the pigs are kept together in sties. No matter how hard you try to keep them clean they are filthy by nature. They eat and enjoy their own as well as their neighbour’s excreta.</p>

<h3 id="pig-is-the-most-shameless-animal">6. Pig is the most shameless animal</h3>

<h3 id="section-5">6. 猪是最没有廉耻的动物</h3>
<p>The pig is the most shameless animal on the face of the earth. It is the only animal that invites its friends to have sex with its mate. In America, most people consume pork. Many times after dance parties, they have swapping of wives; i.e. many say “you sleep with my wife and I will sleep with your wife”. If you eat pigs then you behave like pigs. We Indians look upon America to be very advanced and sophisticated. Whatever they do, we follow after a few years. According to an article in Island magazine, this practice of swapping wives has become common in the affluent circles of Mumbai.</p>

<p>猪是地球上最没有廉耻的动物，它们是唯一一种会邀请朋友和自己配偶进行交媾的动物。在美国，大部分人食用猪肉。舞会之后，他们经常相互交换妻子。比如，很多人会这样说”你和我的妻子睡觉，我和你的妻子睡觉”。如果你食用猪肉，你的行为就会变成猪一样。我们印度人眼中认为美国很高级很厉害。如果他们做什么，我们也跟着效仿，不出几年，根据Island magazine的一篇文章，换妻就会在孟买的富人圈里很普遍。</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[从保险投保费用看男女健康对比]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/07/man-inflection-point-is-47-year-old/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T18:01:44+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/07/man-inflection-point-is-47-year-old</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>下表是某寿险保费列表：</p>

<!--more-->

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>投保年龄</td>
      <td>男</td>
      <td>女</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>30岁</td>
      <td>260</td>
      <td>280</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>…</td>
      <td>…</td>
      <td>…</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>47岁</td>
      <td>1130</td>
      <td>1180</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>48岁</td>
      <td>1290</td>
      <td>1270</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>…</td>
      <td>…</td>
      <td>…</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>64岁</td>
      <td>5190</td>
      <td>3770</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>65岁</td>
      <td>5640</td>
      <td>4030</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>从保费列表可以看出，男女同样年龄相比：47岁前（包含47岁），男人比较不容易产生健康问题，而女人比较容易产生健康问题；47岁后（不含47岁），男人更容易产生健康问题，而女人反到不容易产生健康问题了。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[反对『中医』理由汇集]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/06/Anti-Traditional-Chinese-medicine/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-06T17:59:58+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/06/Anti-Traditional-Chinese-medicine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="section">中药制剂是大分子，容易造成肾衰</h3>
<p>中药制剂是大分子，输液进入血液循环系统，造成肾衰。
<a href="http://zhongyi.ifeng.com/news/pfmf/20101/33509.shtml">http://zhongyi.ifeng.com/news/pfmf/20101/33509.shtml</a></p>

<h3 id="section-1">马兜铃酸造成肾衰</h3>
<p>马兜铃酸造成肾衰，存在众多中药配方中</p>

<h3 id="section-2">中药安神的机理是让人重金属中毒</h3>
<p>中药安神的机理是让人硫化汞（包含在朱砂中）轻微中毒，让人萎靡、反应迟钝，达到安神镇静效果</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="section-3">掺加西药成分</h3>
<p>有些中药有效成分实为西药，或者人工掺加西药成分提高表面效果。</p>

<p>台湾药品食品检验局所出具的检查报告：《（民国）九十八年度調製劑中藥檢出西藥成分之分析》<a href="http://www.fda.gov.tw/tc/includes/GetFile.ashx?id=25&amp;chk=b4e40fbd-f8dd-4b56-9850-97d484aa0d67&amp;mid=141&amp;name=fdContent" title="九十八年度調製劑中藥檢出西藥成分之分析.pdf">报告下载</a>。报告中指出中药人工掺入次数最多的西药成分是：咖啡因。掺加咖啡因的结果就是吃了药后很快症状感觉好了很多，因为咖啡因可以兴奋神经。</p>

<h3 id="section-4">历史上的废弃中医活动</h3>
<p><a href="http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%BC%A2%E6%96%B9%E5%8C%BB%E5%AD%A6">汉方医学</a>为日本的传统医学，由中医学发展而来。日本明治维新时期被日本政府勒令取缔，全部由西医接管,后来实行”废医保药”，医术废除，保留部分药方。<br />
民国初始，教育法没有把中医学列入教育内容，之后1929年通过了废除旧医法案，后因中医界人士强烈反对，实际并未推行。<br />
新中国建国初，卫生部曾提议废除中医，没被中央采纳。文革时中医受政策性扶持，快速发展。1982年新宪法明确“发展现代医药和我国传统医药”，中医和西医并重发展。</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I have a dream]]></title>
    <link href="http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/03/i-have-a-dream/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T06:53:52+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://xixitalk.github.com/blog/2013/06/03/i-have-a-dream</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>对带小院子的房子真是没有抵抗力啊。</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
